<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="">

  <title>Tutorial</title>

  <para>CMView is an interactive Contact Map viewer for protein 
  structures. CMView will allow you to display the contact map and 
  interact with it as well as to show features of the contact map in 
  the corresponding 3-dimensional structure by using the PyMol 
  molecular viewer.</para>

  <sect1>

    <title>Viewing a Contact Map</title>

    <sect2>

      <title>Loading a Contact Map/Structure</title>

      <para>The first step to get your contact map on screen is to load 
      it by using <guimenuitem>Load from</guimenuitem> from the 
      <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu. Here there are many options for the 
      source of your data:</para>

      <orderedlist>

        <listitem>

          <para><guimenuitem>Online PDB</guimenuitem> which will 
          download the PDB data for your chosen 4 letter PDB code 
          directly from the Protein Data Bank&apos;s web</para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

          <para><guimenuitem>PDB File</guimenuitem>, if what you have 
          is a model output of a molecular modeling program in PDB 
          format, then choose this option to load your data</para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

          <para><guimenuitem>CASP RR File</guimenuitem>, to load CASP 
          residue-residue contact predictions. You can also save files 
          with this format with Save to-&gt; CASP RR File</para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

          <para><guimenuitem>Contact Map File</guimenuitem> refers to 
          CMView&apos;s own format, you can choose this if you 
          previously saved a file from CMView in this format.</para>

        </listitem>

      </orderedlist>

      <para>For this example we will load from Online PDB the PDB entry 
      1bxy, with chain code A. In the load dialog</para>

      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/load_dialog.png"
       width=""/></para>

      <para>we can then choose the contact type and distance cutoff: we 
      take Ca (for C-alpha) and 8.0 Å as cutoff. After clicking OK the 
      contact map is displayed and the 3D structure is loaded to the 
      PyMol molecular viewer:</para>

      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="" width=""/></para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2>

      <title>Working with the Contact Map</title>

      <para>Some useful things you can do once your contact map has 
      been loaded are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>

          <para>Select contacts: rectangle select, fill select, 
          diagonal select. While on diagonal mode the sequence 
          separation will be shown together with the coordinates in the 
          lower left corner.</para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

          <para>Show the distance map overlaid (
          <guimenuitem>View</guimenuitem> menu). You can still select 
          contacts while the distance map is shown</para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

          <para>Click on the <guibutton>Info<inlinegraphic fileref="images/information.png" width=""/></guibutton> button to get 
          a full report on the contact map: number of contacts, 
          sequence etc.</para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

          <para>The top and left rulers show the color coded secondary 
          structure elements: blue for alpha-helix, red for beta-sheet, 
          green for turns. You can select contacts between 2 secondary 
          structure elements by first clicking on the first element in 
          the top ruler and then on the second element on the left 
          ruler. You will get something like:</para>

          <para><inlinegraphic fileref="" width=""/></para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

          <para>Some other useful selections for secondary structure 
          elements can also be done from the <guimenu>View</guimenu> 
          menu: helix-helix contacts, strand-strand and intra/inter 
          secondary structure elements contacts.</para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

          <para>Select neighborhoods, i.e. all the contacts for a given 
          residue. Just choose the <guimenuitem>Neighborhood Selection 
          Mode</guimenuitem> and click on the ruler: all neighbors of 
          the chosen residue will be selected. If you click instead on 
          the contact map you will get the neighbors for the 2 residues 
          of the clicked residue pair. For instance if you click on 
          cell (26,43) one gets all neighbors of residue 26 and all 
          neighbors of residue 43. Here we present this in the contact 
          map view, in a graph representation and in the 3-dimensional 
          structure:</para>

        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="" width=""/></para>

      <para>At any time while navigating around the contact map or the 
      residue rulers you will always be able to see the contact map 
      coordinates of the current contact or residue: residue number, 
      residue type and secondary structure. You can also view the 
      original author assigned PDB residue numbers if you switch the 
      appropriate option on in the <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu (only 
      if structure was loaded from Online PDB).</para>

      <para>Remember in all selections above, you can always use 
      CTRL+click to add to the current selection.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2>

      <title>Interacting with PyMol</title>

      <para>Here is where CMView becomes most useful. After selecting 
      residue/contacts in the contact map we can then view their 
      correspondence on the 3-dimensional protein structure by using 
      the PyMol molecular viewer. Commands are sent directly and 
      interactively to PyMol. There are two functions:</para>

      <orderedlist>

        <listitem>

          <para><guimenuitem>Show selected contacts in 
          3D</guimenuitem>: will show the selected contacts as distance 
          objects between the C-alpha atoms of the 2 residues part of 
          the contact. As well as the distance object a selection is 
          created in PyMol which contains all residues present in the 
          contact selection.</para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

          <para><guimenuitem>Show residue pair as edge in 
          3D</guimenuitem> (available from the context menu): will show 
          the distance between the current (where you right-clicked) 
          pair of residues as a distance object in PyMol.</para>

        </listitem>

      </orderedlist>

      <para>As an example here we show contacts between secondary 
      structures element for our structure1bxy. Corresponding to each 
      function in the Select menu we have: a,b) helix-helix contacts, 
      c,d) strand-strand contacts, e,f) contacts within SS elements and 
      finally g,h) contacts between SS elements.</para>

      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="" width=""/></para>

      <para>Of course PyMol still works as usual so that it is possible 
      to do other things with the selections: highlighting or showing 
      different representations like sticks, spheres etc.</para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>

    <title>Comparing two contact maps</title>

    <sect2>

      <title>Loading the second contact map. Alignments.</title>

      <para>As an interesting example for the contact map comparison 
      feature we will use a CASP7 prediction. We want to compare the 
      target T0354 to a good prediction. So first we load the 
      <ulink>real structure</ulink> from the PDB file (same procedure 
      as before) and then the <ulink>prediction</ulink> by using 
      <guimenu>Compare</guimenu> -&gt; <guimenuitem>Load Second 
      Structure From</guimenuitem> -&gt; <guimenuitem>PDB 
      File</guimenuitem>. As before we choose Ca as contact type and 
      8.0 Å distance cutoff.</para>

      <para>After pressing OK the second contact map is calculated and 
      a dialog comes up to choose what type of alignment we want:</para>

      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="" width=""/></para>

      <para>For this case we have two structures with the same sequence 
      so we can simply select Needleman-Wunsch which will do the 
      trivial alignment. The second contact map is displayed and at the 
      same time the corresponding structure is loaded to PyMol 
      superimposed to the first structure:</para>

      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="" width=""/></para>

      <para />

      <para>CMView offers here also a structural alignment (SADP) based 
      on maximum contact map overlap that would be useful when we have 
      distant sequences. See CMView&apos;s <ulink url="manual.html">
      full reference</ulink> for more info about SADP. As a last 
      alternative you can also load your own alignment from a FASTA 
      file.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2>

      <title>Comparing</title>

      <para>The pairwise comparison mode shows the two contact maps 
      with contacts in 3 colors:</para>

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>

          <para>black for common contacts</para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

          <para>pink for contacts unique to the first structure (the 
          real structure)</para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

          <para>green for contacts unique to the second structure (the 
          prediction)</para>

        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For our example of prediction against real this allows us 
      to see at a glance over-predicted (pink) and under-predicted 
      contacts (green).</para>

      <para>It is possible to switch between displaying each of the 
      sets with the 
      <guibutton>toggle buttons 
      <inlinegraphic fileref="images/page_copy.png" width=""/>
      <inlinegraphic fileref="images/page_add.png" width=""/>
      <inlinegraphic fileref="images/page_delete.png" width=""/>
      </guibutton> 
      in the tool 
      bar. Selections always refer to the currently displayed 
      set.</para>

      <para>As in single mode above, the coordinates are displayed in 
      the lower left corner this time for the two structures. The 
      <guibutton>Info
      <inlinegraphic fileref="images/information.png" width=""/>
      </guibutton> function will also display now 
      information for both structures including the numbers of common 
      contacts and unique contacts to each structure.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2>

      <title>Interacting with PyMol</title>

      <para>Finally as before we can also interactively send contacts 
      to PyMol. In the pairwise case it gets more interesting because 
      we get a clear comparison of contacts made/not made by the two 
      structures. We will get now yellow edges in both structures for 
      the common contacts, pink edges for the contacts only in the 
      first structure and green edges for contacts only in the second 
      structure. Correspondingly dashed pink/green edges will be 
      displayed representing the absent (not-made) contacts in the 
      opposite structures.</para>

      <para>As an example we select the green contacts within the red 
      rectangle in b) below. For clarity we have separated the two 
      structures and highlighted residues with colors and spheres in 
      PyMol: c) contacts present in the second structure with solid 
      green edges, a) matching (from alignment) contacts absent in the 
      second structure, dashed pink edges.</para>

      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="" width=""/></para>

      <para>Two extra functions are available in the pairwise 
      comparison mode:</para>

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>

          <para>Superimpose from Selection will superimpose the two 
          structures in PyMol doing a best fit of residues from the 
          selected contacts.</para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

          <para>Show Corresponding Residues From Selection will show 
          the alignment matching pairs for the contacts selected.</para>

        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

</article>

